<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>data-viz | Bruno Messias</title><link>/tag/data-viz/</link><atom:link href="/tag/data-viz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>data-viz</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Bruno Messias</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>/images/icon_hucd6a3d413e7b81060a1d462b35f64cf9_5018_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>data-viz</title><link>/tag/data-viz/</link></image><item><title>GSoC- Google Summer of Code 2021 Final Work Product</title><link>/post/2021-23-08-gsoc-devmessias-final-report/2021-23-08-gsoc-devmessias-final-report/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/post/2021-23-08-gsoc-devmessias-final-report/2021-23-08-gsoc-devmessias-final-report/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Detailed weekly tasks, progress and work done can be found
&lt;a href="https://blogs.python-gsoc.org/en/demvessiass-blog/google-summer-of-code-final-work-product-3/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We have changed some points of my project in the first meeting.
Specifically, we focused the efforts into developing a streaming system
using the WebRTC protocol that could be used in more generic scenarios
than just the network visualization. In addition to that, we have opted
to develop the network visualization for fury as a separated repository
and package available
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>. The
name Helios was selected for this new network visualization system based
on the Fury rendering pipeline.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="proposed-objectives">Proposed Objectives&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Create a streaming system (stadia-like) for FURY
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Should work in a low-bandwidth scenario&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Should allow user interactions and collaboration across the
Internet using a web-browser&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Helios Network System objectives:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Implement the Force-Directed Algorithm with examples&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Implement the ForceAtlas2 algorithm using cugraph with examples&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Implement Minimum-Distortion Embeddings algorithm (PyMDE) and
examples&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Non-blocking network algorithms computation avoiding the GIL
using the Shared Memory approach&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create the documentation and the actions for the CI&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stretch Goals:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Create an actor in FURY to draw text efficiently using shaders&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add support to draw millions of nodes using FURY&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add support to control the opengl state on FURY&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="objectives-completed">Objectives Completed&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Create a streaming system (stadia-like) for FURY&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are several reasons to have a streaming system for data
visualization. Because I am doing my Ph.D. in developing country, I
always need to think of the less expensive solutions to use the
computational resources available. For example, with the GPU&amp;rsquo;s
prices increasing, it is necessary to share the a single machine
with GPU with other users at different locations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To construct the streaming system for my project we have opted to
follow three main properties and behaviors:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>avoid blocking the code execution in the main thread (where the
vtk/fury instance resides)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>work inside of a low bandwidth environment&lt;/li>
&lt;li>make it easy and cheap to share the rendering result. For
example, using the free version of &lt;code>ngrok&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>To achieve the first property we need to circumvent the GIL and
allow python code to execute in parallel. Using the threading module
alone is not good enough to reach real parallelism as Python calls
in the same process can not execute concurrently. In addition to
that, to achieve better organization it is desirable to define the
server system as an uncoupled module from the rendering pipeline.
Therefore, I have chosen to employ the multiprocessing approach for
that. The second and third property can be only achieved choosing a
suitable protocol for transfering the rendered results to the
client. We have opted to implement two streaming protocols: the
MJPEG and the WebRTC. The latter is more suitable for low-bandwidth
scenarios [1].&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The image below shows a simple representation of the streaming
system.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The video below shows how our streaming system works smothly and can
be easily integrated inside of a Jupyter notebook.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6979335/130284952-2ffbf117-7119-4048-b7aa-428e0162fb7a.mp4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Video: WebRTC Streaming +
Ngrok&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6979335/130284261-20e84622-427e-4a59-a46f-6a33f5473025.mp4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Video: WebRTC Streaming +
Jupyter&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pull Requests:&lt;/em> * &lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/480">https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/480&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>2D and 3D marker actor&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This feature gave FURY the ability to efficiently draw millions of
markers and impostor 3D spheres. This feature was essential for the
development of Helios. This feature work with signed distance fields
(SDFs) you can get more information about how SDFs works here [4]
.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The image below shows 1 million of markers rendered using an Intel
HD graphics 3000.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6979335/116004971-70927780-a5db-11eb-8363-8c0757574eb4.png" alt="image1">&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Fine-Tunning the OpenGl State&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sometimes users may need to have finer control on how OpenGL will
render the actors. This can be useful when they need to create
specialized visualization effects or to improve the performance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this PR I have worked in a feature that allows FURY to control
the OpenGL context created by VTK&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pull Request:&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/432">https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/432&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Helios Network Visualization Lib: Network Layout Algorithms&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Case 1:&lt;/strong> Suppose that you need to monitor a hashtag and build a
social graph. You want to interact with the graph and at the same
time get insights about the structure of the user interactions. To
get those insights you can perform a node embedding using any kind
of network layout algorithm, such as force-directed or minimum
distortion embeddings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Case 2:&lt;/strong> Suppose that you are modelling a network dynamic such as
an epidemic spreading or a Kuramoto model. In some of those network
dynamics a node can change the state and the edges related to the
node must be deleted. For example, in an epidemic model a node can
represent a person who died due to a disease. Consequently, the
layout of the network must be recomputed to give better insights.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the described cases, if we want a better (UX) and at the same
time a more practical and insightful application of Helios, the
employed layout algorithms should not block any kind of computation
in the main thread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In Helios we already have a lib written in C (with a python wrapper)
which performs the force-directed layout algorithm using separated
threads avoiding the GIL problem and consequently avoiding blocking
the main thread. But what about the other open-source network layout
libs available on the internet? Unfortunately, most of those libs
have not been implemented like Helios force-directed methods and
consequently, if we want to update the network layout the Python
interpreter will block the computation and user interaction in your
network visualization.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My solution for having PyMDE and CuGraph-ForceAtlas not blocking the
main thread was to break the network layout method into two
different types of processes: A and B and communicate both process
using the Shared Memory approach. You can more information about
this PR through my following posts [2], [3].&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The image below show an example that I made and is available at
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/blob/main/docs/examples/viz_mde.py">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/blob/main/docs/examples/viz_mde.py&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6979335/125310065-a3a9f480-e308-11eb-98d9-0ff5406a0e96.gif" alt="image2">
&lt;em>Pull Requests:&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>MDE Layout:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/6">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/6&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>CuGraph ForceAtlas2&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/13">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/13&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Force-Directed and MDE improvements&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/14">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/14&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Helios Network Visualization Lib: Visual Aspects&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve made several stuffs to give Helios a better visual aspects. One of
them was to give a smooth real-time network layout animations. Because
the layout computations happens into a different process that the
process responsible to render the network was necessary to record the
positions and communicate the state of layout between both process.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The GIF below shows how the network layout through IPC behaved before
these modification&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>below, you can see how after those modifications the visual aspect is
better.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pull Requests:&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>OpenGL SuperActors:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/1">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/1&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Fixed the flickering effect&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/10">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/10&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Improvements in the network node visual aspects&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/15">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/15&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Smooth animations when using IPC layouts&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/17">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/17&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Helios Network Visualization Lib: CI and Documentation&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Because Helios was an project that begins in my GSoC project It was
necessary to create the documentation, hosting and more. Now we have a
online documentation available at &lt;a href="https://heliosnetwork.io/">https://heliosnetwork.io/&lt;/a> altough
the documentation still need some improvements.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below is presented the Helios Logo which was developed by my mentor
Filipi Nascimento.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pull Requests:&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>CI and pytests:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/5">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/5&lt;/a>,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/20">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/20&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Helios Logo, Sphinx Gallery and API documentation&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/18">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/18&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Documentation improvements:&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/8">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/8&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Objectives in Progress&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Draw texts on FURY and Helios&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This two PRs allows FURY and Helios to draw millions of characters
in VTK windows instance with low computational resources
consumptions. I still working on that, finishing the SDF font
rendering which the theory behinds was developed here [5].&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pull Requests:&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/24">https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/24&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/489">https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/489&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{=html}">&amp;lt;/center&amp;gt;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>GSoC weekly Blogs&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Weekly blogs were added to the FURY Website.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pull Requests:&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>First Evaluation:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/476">https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/476&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Second Evaluation:&lt;/strong> TBD&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="references">References&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>[1] ( Python GSoC - Post #1 - A Stadia-like system for data
visualization - demvessias s Blog, n.d.;
&lt;a href="https://blogs.python-gsoc.org/en/demvessiass-blog/post-1-a-stadia-like-system-for-data-visualization/">https://blogs.python-gsoc.org/en/demvessiass-blog/post-1-a-stadia-like-system-for-data-visualization/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] Python GSoC - Post #2: SOLID, monkey patching a python issue and
network layouts through WebRTC - demvessias s Blog, n.d.;
&lt;a href="https://blogs.python-gsoc.org/en/demvessiass-blog/post-2-solid-monkey-patching-a-python-issue-and-network-layouts-through-webrtc/">https://blogs.python-gsoc.org/en/demvessiass-blog/post-2-solid-monkey-patching-a-python-issue-and-network-layouts-through-webrtc/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[3] Python GSoC - Post #3: Network layout algorithms using IPC
-demvessias s Blog,
n.d.)&lt;a href="https://blogs.python-gsoc.org/en/demvessiass-blog/post-3-network-layout-algorithms-using-ipc/">https://blogs.python-gsoc.org/en/demvessiass-blog/post-3-network-layout-algorithms-using-ipc/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[4] Rougier, N.P., 2018. An open access book on Python, OpenGL and
Scientific Visualization [WWW Document]. An open access book on
Python, OpenGL and Scientific Visualization. URL
&lt;a href="https://github.com/rougier/python-opengl">https://github.com/rougier/python-opengl&lt;/a> (accessed 8.21.21).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[5] Green, C., 2007. Improved alpha-tested magnification for vector
textures and special effects, in: ACM SIGGRAPH 2007 Courses on -SIGGRAPH
&amp;lsquo;07. Presented at the ACM SIGGRAPH 2007 courses, ACM Press, San Diego,
California, p. 9. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/1281500.1281665">https://doi.org/10.1145/1281500.1281665&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>GSoC- SDF fonts and OpenGL</title><link>/post/2021-16-08-gsoc-devmessias-11/2021-16-08-gsoc-devmessias-11/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/post/2021-16-08-gsoc-devmessias-11/2021-16-08-gsoc-devmessias-11/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="what-did-i-do-this-week">What did I do this week?&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="fury">FURY&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/489" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR fury-gl/fury#489:&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>| I&amp;rsquo;ve created the PR that will allow FURY to draw hundreds thousands of
labels using texture maps. By default, this PR give to FURY three
pre-built texture maps using different fonts. However, is quite easy
to create new fonts to be used in a visualization.
| It&amp;rsquo;s was quite hard to develop the shader code and find the correct
positions of the texture maps to be used in the shader. Because we
used the freetype-py to generate the texture and packing the glyps.
However, the lib has some examples with bugs. But fortunelly, now
everthing is woking on FURY. I&amp;rsquo;ve also created two different examples
to show how this PR works.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>*
The first example, viz_huge_amount_of_labels.py, shows that feature has a realy good performance. The user can
draw hundreds of thounsands of characters in a regular computer.
![](https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6979335/129643743-6cb12c06-3415-4a02-ba43-ccc97003b02d.png)
* The second example, viz_billboad_labels.py, shows the different behaviors of the label actor. In addition, presents
to the user how to create a new texture atlas font to be used across different visualizations.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/437" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR fury-gl/fury#437:&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Fix: avoid multiple OpenGl context on windows using asyncio&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>The streaming system must be generic, but opengl and vtk behaves in uniques ways in each Operating System. Thus, can be tricky
to have the same behavior acrros different OS. One hard stuff that we founded is that was not possible to use my
TimeIntervals objects (implemented with threading module) with vtk. The reason for this impossibility is because we can't use
vtk in windows in different threads. But fortunely, moving from the threading (multithreading) to the asyncio approcach (concurrency)
have fixed this issue and now the streaming system is ready to be used anywhere.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Flickering&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Finally, I could found the cause of the flickering effect on the streaming system.
This flickering was appearing only when the streaming was created using the Widget object.
The cause seems to be a bug or a strange behavior from vtk.
Calling
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>iren.MouseWheelForwardEvent() or&lt;/p>
&lt;p>iren.MouseWheelBackwardEvent() inside of a thread without invoking the
Start method from a vtk instance produces a memory corruption.
Fortunately, I could fix this behavior and now the streaming system is
working without this glitch effect.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>FURY/Helios
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/24" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR fury-gl/helios#24 :&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This uses the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/489" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PRfury-gl/fury#489:&lt;/a> to give
the network label feature to helios. Is possible to draw node labels,
update the colors, change the positions at runtime. In addition, when a
network layout algorithm is running this will automatically update the
node labels positions to follow the nodes across the screen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6979335/129642582-fc6785d8-0e4f-4fdd-81f4-b2552e1ff7c7.png" alt="image1">&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/23" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR fury-gl/helios#23:
Merged.&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This PR granted compatibility between IPC Layouts and Windows. Besides
that , now is quite easier to create new network layouts using inter
process communication&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="did-i-get-stuck-anywhere">Did I get stuck anywhere?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I did not get stuck this week.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>GSoC- Network layout algorithms using IPC</title><link>/post/2021-07-12-gsoc-devmessias-6/2021-07-12-gsoc-devmessias-6/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/post/2021-07-12-gsoc-devmessias-6/2021-07-12-gsoc-devmessias-6/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi all. In the past weeks, I&amp;rsquo;ve been focusing on developing Helios; the
network visualization library for FURY. I improved the visual aspects of
the network rendering as well as implemented the most relevant network
layout methods.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post I will discuss the most challenging task that I faced to
implement those new network layout methods and how I solved it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-problem-network-layout-algorithm-implementations-with-a-blocking-behavior">The problem: network layout algorithm implementations with a blocking behavior&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Case 1:&lt;/strong> Suppose that you need to monitor a hashtag and build a
social graph. You want to interact with the graph and at the same time
get insights about the structure of the user interactions. To get those
insights you can perform a node embedding using any kind of network
layout algorithm, such as force-directed or minimum distortion
embeddings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Case 2:&lt;/strong> Suppose that you are modelling a network dynamic such as an
epidemic spreading or a Kuramoto model. In some of those network
dynamics a node can change the state and the edges related to the node
must be deleted. For example, in an epidemic model a node can represent
a person who died due to a disease. Consequently, the layout of the
network must be recomputed to give better insights.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In described cases if we want a better (UX) and at the same time a more
practical and insightful application of Helios layouts algorithms
shouldn&amp;rsquo;t block any kind of computation in the main thread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In Helios we already have a lib written in C (with a python wrapper)
which performs the force-directed layout algorithm using separated
threads avoiding the GIL problem and consequently avoiding the blocking.
But and the other open-source network layout libs available on the
internet? Unfortunately, most of those libs have not been implemented
like Helios force-directed methods and consequently, if we want to
update the network layout the python interpreter will block the
computation and user interaction in your network visualization. How to
solve this problem?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-is-using-the-python-threading-is-not-a-good-solution">Why is using the python threading is not a good solution?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>One solution to remove the blocking behavior of the network layout libs
like PyMDE is to use the threading module from python. However, remember
the GIL problem: only one thread can execute python code at once.
Therefore, this solution will be unfeasible for networks with more than
some hundreds of nodes or even less! Ok, then how to solve it well?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="ipc-using-python">IPC using python&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As I said in my previous posts I&amp;rsquo;ve created a streaming system for data
visualization for FURY using webrtc. The streaming system is already
working and an important piece in this system was implemented using the
python SharedMemory from multiprocessing. We can get the same ideas from
the streaming system to remove the blocking behavior of the network
layout libs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My solution to have PyMDE and CuGraph-ForceAtlas without blocking was to
break the network layout method into two different types of processes: A
and B. The list below describes the most important behaviors and
responsibilities for each process&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Process A:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Where the visualization (NetworkDraw) will happen&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create the shared memory resources: edges, weights, positions,
info..&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Check if the process B has updated the shared memory resource which
stores the positions using the timestamp stored in the info_buffer&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Update the positions inside of NetworkDraw instance&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Process B:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Read the network information stored in the shared memory resources:
edges , weights, positions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Execute the network layout algorithm&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Update the positions values inside of the shared memory resource&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Update the timestamp inside of the shared memory resource&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I used the timestamp information to avoid unnecessary updates in the
FURY/VTK window instance, which can consume a lot of computational
resources.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-have-i-implemented-the-code-for-a-and-b">How have I implemented the code for A and B?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Because we need to deal with a lot of different data and share them
between different processes I&amp;rsquo;ve created a set of tools to deal with
that, take a look for example in the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/blob/main/helios/layouts/ipc_tools.py#L111" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ShmManagerMultiArrays
Object&lt;/a>
, which makes the memory management less painful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I'm breaking the layout method into two different processes. Thus I&amp;rsquo;ve
created two abstract objects to deal with any kind of network layout
algorithm which must be performed using inter-process-communication
(IPC). Those objects are:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/devmessias/helios/blob/a0a24525697ec932a398db6413899495fb5633dd/helios/layouts/base.py#L65" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NetworkLayoutIPCServerCalc&lt;/a>
; used by processes of type B and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/devmessias/helios/blob/a0a24525697ec932a398db6413899495fb5633dd/helios/layouts/base.py#L135" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NetworkLayoutIPCRender&lt;/a>
; which should be used by processes of type A.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ll not bore you with the details of the implementation. But let&amp;rsquo;s take
a look into some important points. As I&amp;rsquo;ve said saving the timestamp
after each step of the network layout algorithm. Take a look into the
method _check_and_sync from NetworkLayoutIPCRender
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/blob/a0a24525697ec932a398db6413899495fb5633dd/helios/layouts/base.py#L266" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.
Notice that the update happens only if the stored timestamp has been
changed. Also, look at this line
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/blob/a0a24525697ec932a398db6413899495fb5633dd/helios/layouts/mde.py#L180" target="_blank" rel="noopener">helios/layouts/mde.py#L180&lt;/a>,
the IPC-PyMDE implementation This line writes a value 1 into the second
element of the info_buffer. This value is used to inform the process A
that everything worked well. I used that info for example in the tests
for the network layout method, see the link
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/blob/a0a24525697ec932a398db6413899495fb5633dd/helios/tests/test_mde_layouts.py#L43" target="_blank" rel="noopener">helios/tests/test_mde_layouts.py#L43&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="results">Results&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Until now Helios has three network layout methods implemented: Force
Directed , Minimum Distortion Embeddings and Force Atlas 2. Here
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/blob/a0a24525697ec932a398db6413899495fb5633dd/docs/examples/viz_helios_mde.ipynb" target="_blank" rel="noopener">docs/examples/viz_helios_mde.ipynb&lt;/a>
you can get a jupyter notebook that I&amp;rsquo;ve a created showing how to use
MDE with IPC in Helios.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the animation below we can see the result of the Helios-MDE
application into a network with a set of anchored nodes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6979335/125310065-a3a9f480-e308-11eb-98d9-0ff5406a0e96.gif" alt="image1">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="next-steps">Next steps&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ll probably focus on the Helios network visualization system.
Improving the documentation and testing the ForceAtlas2 in a computer
with cuda installed. See the list of opened
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener">issues&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="summary-of-most-important-pull-requests">Summary of most important pull-requests:&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>IPC tools for network layout methods (helios issue #7)
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury-gl/helios/pull/6&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New network layout methods for fury (helios issue #7)
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury-gl/helios/pull/9&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/14" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury-gl/helios/pull/14&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/13" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury-gl/helios/pull/13&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Improved the visual aspects and configurations of the network
rendering(helios issue #12)
&lt;a href="https://github.com/devmessias/helios/tree/fury_network_actors_improvements">https://github.com/devmessias/helios/tree/fury_network_actors_improvements&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tests, examples and documentation for Helios (helios issues #3 and
#4)
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury-gl/helios/pull/5&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reduced the flickering effect on the FURY/Helios streaming system
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/10" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury-gl/helios/pull/10&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/437/commits/a94e22dbc2854ec87b8c934f6cabdf48931dc279" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury-gl/fury/pull/437/commits/a94e22dbc2854ec87b8c934f6cabdf48931dc279&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>GSoC- Bugs!</title><link>/post/2021-06-21-gsoc-devmessias-3/2021-06-21-gsoc-devmessias-3/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/post/2021-06-21-gsoc-devmessias-3/2021-06-21-gsoc-devmessias-3/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what-did-you-do-this-week">What did you do this week?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/422/commits/8a0012b66b95987bafdb71367a64897b25c89368" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR fury-gl/fury#422
(merged):&lt;/a>
Integrated the 3d impostor spheres with the marker actor.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/422" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR fury-gl/fury#422
(merged):&lt;/a> Fixed some
issues with my maker PR which now it's merged on fury.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/432" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR fury-gl/fury#432&lt;/a>
I've made some improvements in my PR which can be used to fine tune
the opengl state on VTK.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/437" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR fury-gl/fury#437&lt;/a>
I've made several improvements in my streamer proposal for FURY
related to memory management.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR fury-gl/helios#1&lt;/a>
First version of async network layout using force-directed.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="did-i-get-stuck-anywhere">Did I get stuck anywhere?&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="a-python-core-issue">A python-core issue&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I've spent some hours trying to discover this issue. But now it's
solved through the commit
&lt;a href="https://github.com/devmessias/fury/commit/071dab85a86ec4f97eba36721b247ca9233fd59e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">devmessias/fury/commit/071dab85&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The 
&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/multiprocessing.shared_memory.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SharedMemory&lt;/a>
from python&amp;gt;=3.8 offers a new a way to share memory resources between
unrelated process. One of the advantages of using the SharedMemory
instead of the RawArray from multiprocessing is that the SharedMemory
allows to share memory blocks without those processes be related with a
fork or spawm method. The SharedMemory behavior allowed to achieve our
jupyter integration and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/437/files#diff-7680a28c3a88a93b8dae7b777c5db5805e1157365805eeaf2e58fd12a00df046" target="_blank" rel="noopener">simplifies the use of the streaming
system&lt;/a>.
However, I saw a issue in the shared memory implementation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s see the following scenario:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>1-Process A creates a shared memory X
2-Process A creates a subprocess B using popen (shell=False)
3-Process B reads X
4-Process B closes X
5-Process A kills B
4-Process A closes X
5-Process A unlink() the shared memory resource X
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The above scenario should work flawless. Calling unlink() in X is the
right way as discussed in the python official documentation. However,
there is a open issue related the unlink method&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://bugs.python.org/issue38119" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Issue:
https://bugs.python.org/issue38119&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/pull/21516" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PR
python/cpython/pull/21516&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Fortunately, I could use a
&lt;a href="https://bugs.python.org/msg388287" target="_blank" rel="noopener">monkey-patching&lt;/a> solution to fix
that meanwhile we wait to the python-core team to fix the
resource_tracker (38119) issue.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-coming-up-next">What is coming up next?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I'm planning to work in the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/432" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury-gl/fury#432&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/helios/pull/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury-gl/helios#1&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>GSoC- A Stadia-like system for data visualization</title><link>/post/2021-06-12-gsoc-devmessias-2/2021-06-12-gsoc-devmessias-2/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/post/2021-06-12-gsoc-devmessias-2/2021-06-12-gsoc-devmessias-2/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi all! In this post I'll talk about the PR
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fury-gl/fury/pull/437" target="_blank" rel="noopener">#437&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are several reasons to have a streaming system for data
visualization. Because I&amp;rsquo;m doing a PhD in a developing country I always
need to think of the cheapest way to use the computational resources
available. For example, with the GPUs prices increasing, it&amp;rsquo;s necessary
to share a machine with a GPU with different users in different
locations. Therefore, to convince my Brazilian friends to use FURY I
need to code thinking inside of the (a) low-budget scenario.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To construct the streaming system for my project I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about the
following properties and behaviors:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>I want to avoid blocking the code execution in the main thread
(where the vtk/fury instance resides).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The streaming should work inside of a low bandwidth environment.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I need an easy way to share the rendering result. For example, using
the free version of ngrok.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>To achieve the property &lt;strong>1.&lt;/strong> we need to circumvent the GIL problem.
Using the threading module alone it&amp;rsquo;s not good enough because we can&amp;rsquo;t
use the python-threading for parallel CPU computation. In addition, to
achieve a better organization it&amp;rsquo;s better to define the server system as
an uncoupled module. Therefore, I believe that multiprocessing-lib in
python will fit very well for our proposes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For the streaming system to work smoothly in a low-bandwidth scenario we
need to choose the protocol wisely. In the recent years the WebRTC
protocol has been used in a myriad of applications like google hangouts
and Google Stadia aiming low latency behavior. Therefore, I choose the
webrtc as my first protocol to be available in the streaming system
proposal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To achieve the third property, we must be economical in adding
requirements and dependencies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Currently, the system has some issues, but it's already working. You
can see some tutorials about how to use this streaming system
&lt;a href="https://github.com/devmessias/fury/tree/feature_fury_stream_client/docs/tutorials/04_stream" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.
After running one of these examples you can easily share the results and
interact with other users. For example, using the ngrok For example,
using the ngrok&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>./ngrok http 8000
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>|&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-does-it-works">How does it works?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The image below it's a simple representation of the streaming system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6979335/121934889-33ff1480-cd1e-11eb-89a4-562fbb953ba4.png" alt="image1">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As you can see, the streaming system is made up of different processes
that share some memory blocks with each other. One of the hardest part
of this PR was to code this sharing between different objects like VTK,
numpy and the webserver. I'll discuss next some of technical issues
that I had to learn/circumvent.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sharing-data-between-process">Sharing data between process&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>We want to avoid any kind of unnecessary duplication of data or
expensive copy/write actions. We can achieve this economy of
computational resources using the multiprocessing module from python.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="multiprocessing-rawarray">multiprocessing RawArray&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>| The
&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/multiprocessing.html#multiprocessing.sharedctypes.RawArray" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RawArray&lt;/a>
from multiprocessing allows to share resources between different
processes. However, there are some tricks to get a better performance
when we are dealing with RawArray's. For example,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/devmessias/fury/tree/6ae82fd239dbde6a577f9cccaa001275dcb58229" target="_blank" rel="noopener">take a look at my
PR in a older
stage.&lt;/a>
In this older stage my streaming system was working well. However, one
of my mentors (Filipi Nascimento) saw a huge latency for
high-resolutions examples. My first thought was that latency was
caused by the GPU-CPU copy from the opengl context. However, I
discovered that I've been using RawArray's wrong in my entire life!
| See for example this line of code
&lt;a href="https://github.com/devmessias/fury/blob/6ae82fd239dbde6a577f9cccaa001275dcb58229/fury/stream/client.py#L101" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fury/stream/client.py#L101&lt;/a>
The code below shows how I've been updating the raw arrays&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>raw_arr_buffer[:] = new_data
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>This works fine for small and medium sized arrays, but for large ones it
takes a large amount of time, more than GPU-CPU copy. The explanation
for this bad performance is available here :
&lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/33853543/demystifying-sharedctypes-performance" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Demystifying sharedctypes
performance.&lt;/a>
The solution which gives a stupendous performance improvement is quite
simple. RawArrays implements the buffer protocol. Therefore, we just
need to use the memoryview:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>memview(arr_buffer)[:] = new_data
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The memview is really good, but there it's a litle issue when we are
dealing with uint8 RawArrays. The following code will cause an
exception:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>memview(arr_buffer_uint8)[:] = new_data_uint8
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>There is a solution for uint8 rawarrays using just memview and cast
methods. However, numpy comes to rescue and offers a simple and a
generic solution. You just need to convert the rawarray to a np
representation in the following way:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>arr_uint8_repr = np.ctypeslib.as_array(arr_buffer_uint8)
arr_uint8_repr[:] = new_data_uint8
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>You can navigate to my repository in this specific
&lt;a href="https://github.com/devmessias/fury/commit/b1b0caf30db762cc018fc99dd4e77ba0390b2f9e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">commit
position&lt;/a>
and test the streaming examples to see how this little modification
improves the performance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="multiprocessing-inside-of-different-operating-systems">Multiprocessing inside of different Operating Systems&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Serge Koudoro, who is one of my mentors, has pointed out an issue of the
streaming system running in MacOs. I don't know many things about
MacOs, and as pointed out by Filipi the way that MacOs deals with
multiprocessing is very different than the Linux approach. Although we
solved the issue discovered by Serge, I need to be more careful to
assume that different operating systems will behave in the same way. If
you want to know more,I recommend that you read this post
&lt;a href="https://britishgeologicalsurvey.github.io/science/python-forking-vs-spawn/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Python:
Forking vs
Spawm&lt;/a>.
And it's also important to read the official documentation from python.
It can save you a lot of time. Take a look what the official python
documentation says about the multiprocessing method&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/6979335/121958121-b0ebb780-cd39-11eb-862a-37244f7f635b.png" alt="image2">
Source:&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/multiprocessing.html">https://docs.python.org/3/library/multiprocessing.html&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>